<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="identity-html.xsl"?>

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
<title>Davenport WebDAV-SMB Gateway</title>
<link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="stylesheet.css"/>
</head>
<body>
    <h1>Davenport WebDAV-SMB Gateway</h1>
<hr/>
<h3>Overview</h3>
<p>
Davenport is a servlet which provides a WebDAV gateway to SMB
shared resources.  Typical usage would be to provide web-based
read and write access to Windows shared drives.
</p>
<p>
WebDAV clients, such as Windows' &quot;Web Folders&quot; can copy files to and
from the shares over HTTP.  Non-WebDAV-capable web browsers can
also access the network, downloading files from shared folders
in a seamless fashion.
</p>
<p>
Users access shared resources using their Windows domain username
and password, so no account configuration is typically needed.
When run over HTTPS, Davenport provides a secure means of
accessing internal shared drives over the internet without
requiring a VPN.
</p>
<h3>Obtaining Davenport</h3>
<p>
Davenport is free software, provided under the
<a href="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/lesser.txt">GNU Lesser General Public License</a>.  It can be obtained from the Davenport SourceForge project site at:
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/davenport">http://sourceforge.net/projects/davenport</a>
</p>
<p>
The download area (from which the software can be obtained directly)
is at:
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=78146">http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=78146</a>
</p>
<h3>Installation</h3>
<p>
The binary distribution of Davenport is provided preinstalled in a
standalone Jetty Servlet container.  This is distributed in zip and
gzipped tar archives for deployment on a variety of platforms; it is also
available as a Linux RPM install (tested on Fedora Core 2, but should be
portable to most other distributions).
</p>
<h4>Zip/Tar Installation</h4>
<p>
Installation is fairly straightforward:
</p>
<ol>
    <li>Expand the .zip or .tgz archive (preserving directory structure).</li>
    <li><a href="configuration.html">Configure the deployment descriptor.</a></li>
</ol>
<h4>RPM Installation (Linux)</h4>
<ol>
    <li>
        Install the RPM:
        <pre>    rpm -Uhvf davenport-x.x.x-1.rpm</pre>
    </li>
    <li><a href="configuration.html">Configure the deployment descriptor.</a></li>
</ol>
<p>
By default, Davenport will be installed to &quot;/opt/davenport&quot;.
</p>
<h3>Getting Started</h3>
<p>
Before starting, make sure you have <a href="configuration.html">tailored the deployment descriptor to your environment</a>.  After configuration is complete,
the Davenport container is ready be started.  The simplest way to do this is
to run &quot;java -jar start.jar&quot; in the Davenport root directory.
Likewise, executing &quot;java -jar stop.jar&quot; will stop the container.
On the Windows platform, double-clicking the .jar files should launch them
as well.
</p>
<p>
After the container has been started, it should be possible to browse SMB
resources using Davenport.  To list the shares on an SMB server
&quot;smbserver&quot; you would enter into your web browser:
</p>
<pre>
    http://davserver:8080/smbserver/
</pre>
<p>
&quot;davserver&quot; is the server on which Davenport is running (by default,
the container will run on port 8080).  This will bring up the default directory
listing, which will look something like this:
</p>
<p>
<img src="directory.jpg"/>
</p>
<p>
This will list all shares on the &quot;smbserver&quot; server; by clicking one
of the shares, files will be listed, and so forth.
</p>
<p>
Clicking the header link at the top of the screen
(&quot;smb://davhost/files/sample/&quot; in the screenshot above) will reopen
the item as a Web Folder in Internet Explorer:
</p>
<p>
<img src="webfolder.jpg"/>
</p>
<p>
You can drag and drop files to and from the Web Folder, create and
delete directories, and perform other file operations.  You can
open a URL as a Web Folder directly by using the &quot;File -&gt; Open&quot;
menu in Internet Explorer, and selecting &quot;Open as Web Folder&quot;.
</p>
<h3>Troubleshooting</h3>
<p>
View the <a href="troubleshooting.html">Davenport Troubleshooting Guide</a>
for issue resolution procedures and contact information.
</p>
<h3>Technical Resources</h3>
<a href="api/index.html">API Documentation</a><br/>
<a href="rfc2518.txt">HTTP Extensions for Distributed Authoring -- WEBDAV (RFC 2518)</a><br/>
<a href="draft-ietf-webdav-rfc2518bis-06.txt">HTTP Extensions for Distributed Authoring -- WebDAV RFC2518 bis (Internet-Draft)</a><br/>
<a href="draft-reschke-webdav-locking-05.txt">Web Distributed Authoring and Versioning (WebDAV) Locking Protocol (Internet-Draft)</a><br/>
<a href="draft-crhertel-smb-url-07.txt">SMB Filesharing URI Scheme (Internet-Draft)</a><br/>
<a href="ntlm.html">The NTLM Authentication Protocol</a><br/>
</body>
</html>
